Frank J. Niedermayer VHP2006/4
CCSU Veterans History Project
Frank J. Niedermayer Papers
Bulk, 1941-1947
1941-1947, 2006
VHP2006/4
CCSU Veterans History Project
110.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
This collection describes the service related experiences and military combat of Frank Joseph Niedermayer during World War II. The collection contains video oral history interview, service records, photographs, and military publications. The materials, which date mainly from 1943 thru 1947, provide evidence of American troop training, deployment, and combat activity, as well as U.S. military moral and courage.
Neidermayer, Frank J., (Frank Joseph), 1922 -
Arrangement note
Series I: Personal Papers
Series II: Publications
Series III: Multi-Media
Biographical/Historical note
Frank J. Niedermayer was drafted into the U.S. Army in April of 1943, while he was living in New Britain, Ct. He went to basic training at Camp Atterbury (IN), where he trained as an infantry soldier. However, after the completion of basic training he was sent to artillery training in Kansas, where he learned to be the 2nd gunner on armored vehicle. While on leave after training, he went back to Connecticut. When he returned to Kansas, he was married to a girl in Topeka, before returning to duty. In May of 1944, his battalion shipped overseas, and landed in England, where they stayed for a month. After a month the armored vehicle division shipped over the English Channel in a convoy of 100 ships, to the shores of France. Niedermayer's armored vehicle battalion lived in their vehicles for the most part. They ate, slept, and worked on the tanks. The battery of armored vehicles was almost always engaged in a battle of some sort, including the Battle for Metz. The war ended while his unit was in Austria, and they returned home for a 30 day leave before shipping to Japan. However, the war in Japan ended while Niedermayer was on leave, and he was instead shipped to Texas to await his discharge. Niedermayer was discharged on October 16, 1945, and he returned to Connecticut where he lived with his family, and worked as an electrician.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
United States. Army. Armored Field Artillery Battalion, 274th.; United States. Army.; Ardennes; Armored vehicles, Military; Belgium; Camp Atterbury (Ind.); Camp Phillips (Kan.); England; Houffalize; Metz (France); Metz, Battle of, Metz, France, 1944; Rhineland (Germany); World War II - - Personal Narrative, American; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- France
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2006/4.I
  - Discharge certificate, Oct. 16, 1945; VHP2006/4.I.1
  - Separation document, Oct. 16, 1945; VHP2006/4.I.2
  - Interview synopsis, Feb. 3, 2006; VHP2006/4.I.3
- Series II: Publications, VHP2006/4.II
  - A History of the 274th Armored Field Artillery Battalion (book), 1946; VHP2006/4.II.1; 59.0 Digital objects
  - 274th Armored Field Artillery Association membership booklet, n.d.; VHP2006/4.II.2; 21.0 Digital objects
- Series III: Multi-Media, VHP2006/4.III
  - Subseries A: Still Images, VHP2006/4.III
    - Frank Niedemayer sitting on porch steps before being drafted into the United States Army. New Britain, CT, 1942; VHP2006/4.III.1
    - Frank Niedemayer posing in uniform. New Britain, CT, 1943; VHP2006/4.III.2
    - Frank Niedemayer in uniform. New Britain, CT, 1943; VHP2006/4.III.3
    - Frank Niedemayer in uniform. Camp Phillips, KS, 1943; VHP2006/4.III.4
    - Frank Niedemayer(kneeling) with four other soldiers. Camp Phillips, KS, 1943; VHP2006/4.III.5
    - Frank Niedemayer (far Left) with six other soldiers in barracks. Camp Phillips, KS, 1943; VHP2006/4.III.6
    - Portrait of Frank Niedemayer in uniform. Salina, KS, 1943; VHP2006/4.III.7
    - Frank Niedemayer in uniform posing with his father Joseph Niedemayer. New Britain, CT, 1945; VHP2006/4.III.8
    - Frank Niedemayer in uniform (right) posing with his uncle John Nemeth. New Britain, CT, 1945; VHP2006/4.III.9
    - Frank Niedemayer in uniform (center) posing with his uncle and his father. New Britain, CT, 1945; VHP2006/4.III.10
    - Frank Niedemayer in uniform (right) posing his wife Grace Nesta Niedemayer, and his father. New Britain, CT, 1945; VHP2006/4.III.11
    - Frank Niedemayer in uniform. New Britain, CT, 1945; VHP2006/4.III.12
    - Frank Niedemayer in uniform with his father and his cousin Emil Blank. New Britain, CT, 1945; VHP2006/4.III.13
    - Frank Niedemayer in uniform with his cousin Emil Blank. New Britain, CT, 1945; VHP2006/4.III.14
    - Frank Niedemayer with his mother Mary Niedemayer (far left), his sister Josephine Niedemayer (second from right), and his father. New Britain, CT, 1945; VHP2006/4.III.15
    - Frank Niedemayer with his sister Josephine (far left),his mother, and his wife. New Britain, CT, 1945; VHP2006/4.III.16
    - Josphine Niedemayer, wearing Frank Niedemayer’s cap, posing with her father. New Britain, CT, 1945; VHP2006/4.III.17
    - Frank Niedemayer and his sister Josephine. New Britain, CT, 1945; VHP2006/4.III.18
    - Frank Niedemayer with his sister, his wife, and his cousin Ann Buchas wearing his cap. New Britain, CT, 1945; VHP2006/4.III.19
    - Mary and Joseph Niedemayer with Frank Niedemayer’s aunts Lena Blank (far left), and Ann Buchas (far right). New Britain, CT, 1945; VHP2006/4.III.20
    - Ann Buchas,Joseph Niedemayer, and Lena Blank. New Britain, CT, 1945; VHP2006/4.III.21
    - Frank Niedemayer with his aunt Ann,his cousin, his wife, and his aunt Lena. New Britain, CT, 1945; VHP2006/4.III.22
    - Frank and grace Niedemayer with their infant daughter Frances Niedemayer. New Britain, CT, 1945; VHP2006/4.III.23
    - Frank Niedemayer’s framed memorabilia. East Berlin, CT, March 2006; VHP2006/4.III.24
    - Frank Niedemayer. Berlin CT, March 2006; VHP2006/4.III.25
  - Subseries B: Moving Images, VHP2006/4.IIIb
    - Oral history interview with Frank Niedemayer, Feb. 3 2006; VHP2006/4.IVb.1; Hurst, Eileen (Disk DVD VHP2006/4, Box VHP Interview 2006)